<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the honourable Christopher Sherard, Esq., eldest son to the right honourable Bennet Lord Sherard, February the 28th, 1681 by T.L. ...</title>
            <author>Laxton, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34511</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14471871</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14471871</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102410</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102410)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1062:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of the honourable Christopher Sherard, Esq., eldest son to the right honourable Bennet Lord Sherard, February the 28th, 1681 by T.L. ...</title>
                  <author>Laxton, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Roycroft for Robert Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: Grief allayed, death sweetned, hope raised.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherard, Christopher, d. 1681.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102410:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102410:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Grief allayed, Death ſweetned, Hope raiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the FUNERAL OF THE HONOURABLE <hi>CHRYSTOPHER
SHERARD,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Eldeſt Son to the RIGHT HONOURABLE
<hi>BENNET</hi> Lord <hi>SHERARD; February</hi> the 28<hi rend="sup">th,</hi> 1681.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. L.</hi> M.A.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. Roycroft,</hi> for <hi>Robert
Clavell</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls Church-yard,</hi>
1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102410:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102410:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth Sherard,</hi>
Fulneſs of true Conſolation in Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAD not your Ladiſhip deſired a Sight of this plain Sermon, I
ſhould ſcarce have aſſumed the Confidence to have preſented it to
your peruſal; but as I receive your deſire as a Command, ſo your
favourable Acceptance will add weight and worth to it. If the witty Cenſurer
ſhall ſay, That I tell him nothing but what he knew lefore; I ſhall be
contented with it, and rejoyce that he was ſo well Inſtructed, and wiſh
alſo that he needed not a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer; howſoever, no man ought to be
offended, that Sermons are not like curious Inquiries after
<hi>New-nothings,</hi> but purſuances of <hi>Old Truths.</hi> I am very
ſenſible your Ladiſhip is furniſhed (from much more Learned
Phyſicians than I am) with very proper Receipts againſt the late cauſe of
your Sorrow; yet I hope (Madam) that this which I here preſent unto you, may
ſomewhat heighten and improve their efficacy: And in ſo doing, I ſhall
eſteem it amongſt thoſe Bleſſings, with which God uſeth to reward
thoſe good Intentions which himſelf firſt puts into our hearts, and then
recompences up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb facs="tcp:102410:3"/>our heads. All Sermons are but Arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
us, unleſs they make us quit our Miſtakes, and ſuffer them in ſome
inſtance and degree to do the work of God upon our Souls. And the ſpecial
deſign of this here preſent (dedicated to your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Patronage and
Protection) is, to deſcribe the greater Lines of our Duty, when our Faces are
bedew'd with Tears, and our Backs cloathed with Mourning: And whatſoever
relliſh your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip may find in the Comment, yet I am ſure the Text,
being carefully laid up in your Religious Breaſt, will be ſound,
wholeſom, and conſolatory; though what I have in much weakneſs perform'd
is only in Duty expreſſing the many and great Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations you daily renew
upon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips Moſt obliged Servant, and devoted
Chaplain, Tho. Laxton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102410:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Theſſ. 4.13.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <p>But I would not have you to be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, Brethren, concerning
them which are aſleep; that ye ſorrow not, even as others which have no
hope.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE weeping Eyes and bleeding Hearts which are ſo plentifully
diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in this Aſſembly, tell you the ſum of my Errand, our
preſent Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Work in hand, a Funeral. The Party deceaſed; a
moſt accompliſht, ingenious, pious, well-natur'd, well-nurtur'd Perſon:
The firſt Son and hopeful Heir to the Great and Generous, Heroick and Ancient
Family of the <hi>Sherards.</hi> The Mourners, not only all preſent, but
abſent, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers as great and conſiderable, as our loſs and tears are
great and wonderful: The Place of Burial, the Sepulcher of his Progenitors.
When <hi>Samuel</hi> died, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25. <hi>all the Iſraelites were
gathered together, and lamented him; and buried him in his Houſe at</hi>
Ramah. To be buried, is an honour; buried in one's own Country, much; in his
own Place, more; <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102410:4"/>with ſolemn Lamentations, moſt of all;
the Saints Honour: For he that ſpends his days, though few, (as this moſt
excellent Branch of Vertue did) upon God and Man, ſhall at the laſt have
all the Honour Heaven and Earth can caſt upon him: A holy and a vertuous Life
ends in an happy and honourable Death. <hi>Joſiah</hi> having received his
Death abroad, is brought home in his Chariot, and much Honour attends him to
his Grave; he is <hi>buried amongst his Fathers;</hi> all <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
nay all <hi>Judah,</hi> and the Neighbouring Towns, are Mourners: God and Man
concurred in this, that <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Name ſhould never dye. Good men
never go to the Grave unlamented, but generally are attended with Mourning,
<hi>as the Mourning of</hi> Hadradrimmon in the Valley of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giddon.</hi>
And here lies the miſtake of <hi>weak and frail man,</hi> that too often
performs actions in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves lawfully good, after an unlawful and
immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate manner. The words therefore that I have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen for our preſent
Subject, are a choice portion of Scripture; teaching us to ſtere our
Courſe, and keep up our Heads, that we neither ſink nor drown in theſe
Waters of Affliction. And though I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now treated on the ſame Text,
yet, at this time, and upon this occaſion, I have renew'd my Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
and adapted them, not only for Matter, but alſo in ſuch Order and Method,
as may be moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the end I propoſe, even, the allaying our
Griefs, and raiſing our Hopes; <hi>I would not have you to be ignorant,</hi>
&amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Scope of the Apoſtle in theſe words, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate
immoderate Sorrow for them that <hi>ſleep in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102410:4"/>
            <p>For the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 'though well inſtructed an
confirm'd in the Faith, and particularly of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> (which
Faith, if it had its full work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, would neceſſarily infer and inforce a
mean in Mourning for deceaſed Chriſtians) yet, it ſeems o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verborn
ſometimes with immoderate Paſſion for their deceaſed Brethren, they
gave way to exceſs of Sorrow. Againſt this Infirmity, the Apoſtle gives
this Exhortation, as a ſeaſonable and wholeſom Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. <hi>I would,
&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Where obſerve, The Subſtance of the Precept, to keep
a Mean in Mourning; not to pour out our ſelves into exceſſive Sorrow for
the Dead.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reaſons to enforce it, interwoven with the Precept.
From, 
<list>
                  <item>1. The Nature of Death; <hi>a Sleep.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The Iſſue of Death; <hi>a hopeful
Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Withal ſecretly taxing and reprehending this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate Sorrow,
as arguing too little knowledge (practical knowledge) of future
Bleſſedneſs; and too much ſavouring of <hi>Gentiliſm,</hi> whoſe
hopes were terminated with this preſent Life, and of the bleſſed ſtate
to come, were altogether hopeleſs. The firſt, in the firſt words, <hi>I
would not have you ignorant;</hi> and the other in the laſt, <hi>even as the
Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The firſt general Oſervation is, 
<q>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Obſ. 1."/> That Chriſtians ought to moderate
their Sorrow for the Dead.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To baniſh indeed all Affections out of the Nature of Man, may be
a part of Stoical, but not Chriſtian Philoſophy. Religion, as it doth not
aboliſh Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <pb n="4" facs="tcp:102410:5"/>but ſanctifie and guide it; nor
deprive us of Senſe, but teacheth us a right uſe of the Senſes; ſo it
deſtroys not the Affections, but orders and huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands them aright; as
<hi>Joſhuah</hi> did dot kill the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites,</hi> but ſubjected them
to the uſe and ſervice of the Tabernacle. They therefore are to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
that ſtupifie Nature, and quench thoſe Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that are implanted in us
by the Finger of God in our firſt Creation; as that rigid Sect the
<hi>Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks,</hi> who would have their Wiſe-man, or Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical Saint
ſo mortified, as in no Accident to Joy, or Grieve, or change a Countenance;
or in any Loſs, even of deareſt Friends, to ſuffer any relenting. Such
pains they took to ceaſe to be Men, that they ſubjected themſelves below
the degree of Beaſts. Patience they may count it, &amp; inſuperable
Fortitude, which is indeed rather the want of <hi>natural affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> condemn'd by the Apoſtle as a
<hi>blockiſh ſtupidity;</hi> and may juſtly fall under that Cenſure, 
<note place="margin">Jer. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thou hast ſmitten them,
but they have not grieved:</hi> For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the death of Friends is a
ſtroke. 
<note place="margin">Ezek. 24.</note> 
               <hi>I will take away the
deſire of thine eyes with a ſtroke;</hi> (ſaith God to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>)
a ſtroke which toucheth all of dear relation; and is it fit the ſtrokes of
God ſhould fall upon a flinty and unrelenting heart? Therefore we find that
<hi>Abraham</hi> mourned for <hi>Sarah; Joſeph</hi> for <hi>Jacob;</hi> the
<hi>Iſraelites</hi> for <hi>Moſes, Aaron, Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> Cuſtomary it was
among the <hi>Jews</hi> to mourn <hi>ſeven days;</hi> ſometimes longer;
with <hi>faſting</hi> and <hi>renting of the Clothes:</hi> This perhaps more
of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, than either of Neceſſity or Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102410:5"/>
            <p>Yet there ought to be a Moderation for them that are <hi>dead in
Christ.</hi> As all our Affections, that they may be uſeful in a Chriſtian
Life, muſt be bankt up within their due Bounds, and bridled with a ſtrong
hand of Grace; neither miſapplied in their Object, nor falling over or
ſhort in their Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: And therefore ſome of the very <hi>Heathen</hi>
have placed the top of Wiſdom in the Moderation of the Affections; their
<hi>Ethicks,</hi> or <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Moral Vertues</hi> being
exerciſed chiefly in this Task: So particularly a ſpecial care is to be had
that they overflow not the Banks in mourning for the Dead. Hence God did forbid
to his People thoſe <hi>Heathen Rites</hi> of <hi>cutting themſelves,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 14.1.</note> and <hi>ſhaving</hi> of the
<hi>hair.</hi> Our bleſſed Saviour, in the caſe of <hi>Jairus</hi> his
Daughter, newly dead, when both the Father and Mother of the Child, and the
Diſciples there preſent opened the Sluce of Tears to their Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
ſets Bounds and Banks to that Paſſion, in theſe words, <hi>Weep not;
ſhe is not dead, but ſleepeth.</hi> For this cauſe he diſliked in their
Solemn Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, the uſe of the Jewiſh Minſtrelſy, the end whereof was
to encreaſe Sorrow by ſad and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Tunes. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deteſtandae ſunt illae lacrymae quae non
habent modum.</hi> Thrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodiae.</note> 
               <hi>Affection</hi> (ſaith One) <hi>in
this Caſe hath need of a Bridle, not a Spur.</hi> St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s
Caution is worthy of Obſervation, <hi>Thoſe Tears are to be deteſted
which have no meaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, ſome of Gods Children have Impotently yielded to the
violence of this Paſſion (as indeed it is moſt eaſie to ſlip into
<hi>Exceſs,</hi> where the Matter about which our Actions are converſant,
is of it ſelf confeſſedly Lawful:) Hence <hi>Rachels</hi> Weeping,
Mourning, and great Lamentation for her <hi>Children, <pb n="6" facs="tcp:102410:6"/>becauſe</hi> (as to her preſent ſenſe) <hi>they were not.</hi>
And <hi>Davids</hi> Paſſionate Ejaculations for <hi>Abſolom; O Abſolom,
&amp;c. would God I had died for thee, &amp;c.</hi> But theſe Examples are
neither commendable nor imitable; and rather Documents of Humane Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
than Precedents of Imitation. And for the laſt; he bewail'd not ſo much, in
St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, his Sons death, as that fearful ſtate
wherein he ſeem'd to die; ſtain'd with horrid <hi>Inceſt</hi> againſt
his Fathers Bed, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural practiſes</hi> againſt his Fathers
Life. How much more comly and Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table was his Demeanour in the Death of his
Child, born to him by <hi>Bethſhabe?</hi> Seeking to the Lord by <hi>Prayer
and Faſting</hi> for the Child, while it was yet alive; 
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.23.</note> but when dead,
<hi>Wherefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhould I faſt? I ſhall go to him, but
he ſhall not return to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, for the ſuppreſſing of this Inordinate Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
take into your ſerious Thoughts theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is Gods doing; and we muſt give him leave to
uſe his own Power and Soveraignty over his Creature, 
<note place="margin">Iſai. 64.2.</note> in whoſe hands <hi>we are
all as Clay in the hands of the Potter.</hi> He that inſpired the Breath of
life, may juſtly recal it: Whatſoever the Weapon be, the Hand is his that
wields it. This one Meditation is enough to ſilence all Repining and
Impatient Thoughts; as to draw from us that hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reſignation of St.
<hi>Paul, 
<note place="margin">Acts 21.14.</note> The Will of the Lord be
fulfilled:</hi> Of <hi>Eli, It is the Lord, let him do what ſeems good in his
ſight:</hi> Of <hi>David, I held my peace, and opened not my Mouth, for it
was thy doing.</hi> This Conſideration allayed <hi>Jobs</hi> Sorrow in 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102410:6"/>the loſs of his Children: He look'd not at the <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
Houſe,</hi> or the <hi>Four Winds</hi> that ſmote it; but at him that
bringeth the <hi>Winds out of his Treaſures;</hi> and therefore ſets up
within himſelf this patient Reſolution, <hi>The Lord giveth, 
<note place="margin">Job. 1.21.</note> and the Lord taketh away;
Bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider the Vanity and Unprofitableneſs of
Exceſſive Sorrow; it profiteth neither the Living, nor the Dead. Not the
<hi>Living: 
<note place="margin">Prov. 12.25.</note> Heavineſs in the heart of
Man bringeth it down, and Worldly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row worketh death.</hi> As Fire lightly
ſprinkled, burns more clearly; too much overwhelm'd gives neither heat nor
light: So moderate Sorrow advantageth the Soul in many Natural, Moral, and
Spiritual Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Immoderate, quencheth the Vigour of the Spirits, and
renders us unfit for every good Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>Again, It profiteth not the <hi>Dead.</hi> Should we fill their
Tombs with Tears, and ſpend our Lives in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, we cannot redeem them.
Exceſſive Sorrow may bring us to them; no Sorrow, Care, or Coſt can bring
them back to us: As <hi>David, I ſhall go to him, but he ſhall not return
to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider the Neceſſity of Dying. Ever ſince that
neceſſitating Law, <hi>Dust thou art, and unto Duſt ſhalt thou
return,</hi> Man is by the Chain of Gods irrevocable Decree tied unto Death.
<hi>It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to all Men once to die;</hi> and who ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint
his Appointment? Whatſoever parts have been acted upon this Stage of
Mortality, <hi>Death</hi> is the <hi>Cataſtrophe,</hi> and the <hi>Grave</hi>
the place of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyring. The Wiſdom of the Wiſe cannot prevent it; the
Tongue of the Eloquent cannot charm it; <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102410:7"/>the Strength of the
Mighty cannot reſiſt it: It Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenceth neither the Gray hairs of the
Aged, nor the Green locks of the Young. No ſwiftneſs can over-run it, no
Proweſs over-match it: No gifts of Nature, priviledges of Place, endowments
of Grace, can free us from the ſtroke of it. Where are thoſe Millions of
Generations, that have hitherto Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled the Earth? Have they not made their
Beds in the Dark? And when they have ſerv'd their time, have they not ſeen
Corruption? And ſhall We think to have our Friends, <hi>Fathers, Mothers,
Husbands, Wives, Children,</hi> exempted from the Univerſal Law of Humane
Nature?</p>
            <p n="4">4. But that which is yet more effectual to moderate Sorrow
for the Dead, is, that <hi>Death</hi> is indeed a Portal and paſſage unto
Life. If indeed they were utterly extinct, ſhut up in Eternal Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
ſome reaſon had we with <hi>Rachel</hi> to Mourn for them, ſuppoſing
that they are not: But we know that they are, and believe that they are happy;
and <hi>that when this Earthly houſe of our tabernacle is diſſolved, we
have a building not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens.</hi> When the
Soul, taking her flight into a ſtate of Bliſs, and leaving behind her this
Clog of Mortality, ſhall be removed an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>computable diſtance from this
Vale of Sin and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. And are we ſorry for this bleſſed Exchange?
ſhall we Mourn for their glorious preferment, whom we profeſs to live with
God? 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spei noſtrae ac Fidei prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores.
Simu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata, ficta, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata, videntur eſſe quae dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus.</hi>
Cyprian.</note> What difference, in this reſpect, between the Hopeleſs
Heathen, and the Profeſſed Chriſtian? St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> thinks it
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruous to Mourn for them in Black, that follow the <hi>Lamb</hi> in
White. This perhaps may ſeem a Flower of Rhetorick; but certainly,
Exceſſive Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102410:7"/>ſhews us to be of a defective Faith:
That Faith can hardly be thought ſincere, unto which we walk ſo contrary in
Practice. Eſpecially ſeeing a very Heathen could ſay, That <hi>we do</hi>
(not <hi>amittere,</hi> but <hi>praemittere</hi>) <hi>not loſe them, but
ſend them before us;</hi> in Hope (as our Faith further teacheth us) to
follow and communicate with them in the ſame Glory and Bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Obſ. 2."/> And this leads me to the next General
part of the Text, the Firſt Reaſon againſt Exceſſive Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for the
Dead, the Nature of Death, <hi>It is a ſleep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sleep,</hi> in phraſe of Scripture, admits of divers
ſenſes; for we find, Firſt,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſleep of Nature:</hi> A binding of the Senſes; 
<note place="margin">Somnus Naturae.</note> a Reſt, ceſſation,
and ſuſpention of them from their Actual operations; and conſequently, 
<note place="margin">Ligatio ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> of all the Members
of the Body from executing their Natural offices and functions. Thus
<hi>Adam</hi> ſlept in Paradice, <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the Ship, <hi>Peter</hi>
in the Priſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The ſleep of Sin:</hi> A ſecure Spiritual
Lethargy. 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Somnus Cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae.</hi> Eph. 5.14. 1 Theſſ. 5.6.</note>
               <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt. Let us not ſleep, as do others; but let us
watch and be ſober;</hi> that is, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from the Grave of Infidelity and
Sin, unto the Life of Faith, the Life of Righteouſneſs; and then to keep
the Eyes of our Souls continually waking, leſt we be inveigled by the Devil
or the Worlds Temptations.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The ſleep of Grace:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Somnus Gratiae.</note> A holy Peace and
Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of Mind, ariſing from the apprehenſion of Gods favour in
Chriſt. <hi>I will lay me down and ſleep.</hi> If <hi>David</hi> can attain
a glimpſe of the light of Gods Countenance, then he will lay him down and
ſleep.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102410:8"/>
            <p n="4">4. 
<note place="margin">Somnus Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri.</note> 
               <hi>The ſleep of the
Grave:</hi> The long ſleep of Death; when the Body lying in the Bed of Duſt
doth reſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til it be awakened by the Sound of the laſt Trumpet. Now to
prevent Error and Miſtake, this Sleep is not to be conceiv'd of the
ſeparated Soul, as ſome have vainly thought; ſuppoſing it to be not
only without Organical by a bodily Inſtrument action, but without all Action:
Not conſidering, that the Soul, even in the ſtate of Union and Commerce
with the Body, hath her proper and Immaterial acts of Thinking, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning,
Judging, &amp;c. Yea, the moſt perfect Acts of the Soul are exerciſed, when
the Bodily Senſes are tied up, as in Extaſies and deep Contemplations.
Beſides, the Spirits of Men, in and after their Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration, are
ſtill Spirits; but without motion and activity they would be no Spirits: For
the Nature and Eſſence of a Spirit conſiſts in Act; and it is not
obſcurely intimate, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.12. that they are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in
<hi>Magnifying and praiſing God.</hi> Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this <hi>Sleep</hi>
therefore to be of the Body in the Grave; a Metaphor very frequent in Holy
Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: 
<note place="margin">Deu. 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>Many of them that ſleep
in the dust of the Earth, ſhall awake.</hi> Of divers of the Kings of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> 'tis ſaid, that they <hi>ſlept with
their Fathers.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> reproving the abuſe of the Holy
Sacrament in the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Church; <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (ſaith
he) <hi>many are ſick and weak among you, and many ſleep.</hi> And St.
<hi>Stephen,</hi> having <hi>commended his Spirit into the hands of Chriſt, 
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Act. 7.59.</note> fell
aſleep.</hi> A Similitude uſed among the Heathen: Hence their diſtinction
of the Greater and Leſſer Sleep. 
<note place="margin">Homer. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> One calls it
<hi>Deaths Brother;</hi> Another, <hi>Deaths Siſter;</hi> Another, <hi>Deaths
Image.</hi> Of one <hi>Gorgias</hi> it is ſaid, That being ſick and heavy
unto <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102410:8"/>Death, and very ſleepy; being ask'd how he did, 
<note place="margin">Virgil. <hi>Stulte quid eſt ſomnus gelidae,
niſi mortis Imago. Jamme ſomnus incipit tradere fratri ſuo.</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> replied, <hi>Now ſleep begins to deliver me up
to his Brother Death.</hi> Theſe, although Ignorant of a Reſurrection,
could eaſily find in Death the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a <hi>Sleep:</hi> Hence our
Graves are called <hi>Beds,</hi> and our Churchyards, <hi>Sleeping-places,</hi>
or <hi>Dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories.</hi> And indeed, if <hi>Death</hi> be a Sleep, the
<hi>Grave</hi> muſt needs be the Bed. 
<note place="margin">Iſai. 57.2.</note> Unto this may fitly be
applied that of the Propht, <hi>They ſhall enter into peace, they ſhall lie
down upon their Beds; each one walking in his uprightneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divers Reaſons may be given of this Similitude; I ſhall pitch
upon two: Firſt, <hi>Sweetneſs of Reſt.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Certainty of
Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Sweetneſs of Reſt. 
<note place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> Bleſſed are the Dead
which die in the Lord, for they reſt from their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> Man is
<hi>born to affliction, as the ſparks fly upwards.</hi> No Family, Age, Sex,
or Condition of Men, but hath experience of Humane Miſeries: A heavy yoak is
laid upon the Sons of Men, from the day of their Birth unto the day of their
Death. Afflictions, like Waves, come rolling one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the end of one
miſery is the beginning of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Hear we not one crying, <hi>My belly, my
belly!</hi> with the Prophet? another, <hi>My head, my head!</hi> with the
<hi>Shunamites</hi> Son? One, <hi>My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my Father!</hi> with
<hi>Eliſha?</hi> another, <hi>My Son, my Son!</hi> with <hi>David?</hi> One
complaining of Cruel Enemies; another of Falſe Friends: One of Sore Labour;
another of Hungry Meals: One of Grief in the Body; another of Sin in the Soul?
Here lies <hi>Jacob</hi> in the Fields, there <hi>Joſeph</hi> in Priſon;
Here <hi>Jeremy</hi> in the Dungeon, there <hi>David</hi> in the Wilderneſs;
<hi>Daniel</hi> among the Lions, the <hi>Three <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102410:9"/>Children</hi>
in the Fiery Furnace. It is not unſignificant that Nature ſends us into the
World, <hi>Weeping;</hi> a ſad preſage of our future Calamity: Such our
Ingreſs, ſuch our Progreſs through this Vale of Tears. So that
<hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> ſeem to be born under one Planet. If Man
had not been, Sorrow upon Earth had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been. And as we ſuffer many Evils,
ſo we do more; the Fleſh continually luſting againſt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and
the Spirit againſt the Fleſh: <hi>ſo that the good which we would, we do
not; and the evil which we would not, that we do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all theſe, this <hi>Sleep</hi> in my Text, gives us a
ſweet diſcharge; the Soul carried into <hi>Abrahams</hi> Boſom. And what
is the Fathers Boſom, but a place of Repoſe unto the Child? The Body laid
up in a Couch of Sacred reſt and ſecurity; ſweetned, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified,
ſeaſoned and perfumed by the moſt precious Death and Burial of Chriſt; 
<note place="margin">Cubile in quo mollius dormit quiſquis durius
ſe en hâc vitâ geſſerit.</note> where our ſleep ſhall be
ſweeter, as our labour hath been harder. The Body no ſooner dead, but it
feels nothing; the Soul no ſooner fled, but it feels it ſelf happy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Certainty of Reſurrection.</hi> Indeed, more
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain than we are of riſing in the Morning, when we go to Bed at Night. 
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.2.</note> 
               <hi>They that ſleep</hi>
(according to <hi>Daniels</hi> Prophecy) <hi>ſhall awake.</hi> The
<hi>Sea</hi> and the <hi>Grave</hi> ſhall deliver up their Dead, as faithful
Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtees and Depoſitaries of that which is committed to them. A Voice will
one day ſound, like that of Chriſt <hi>(who is the Reſurrection and the
Life)</hi> to <hi>Lazarus; Lazarus come forth:</hi> Or like that in the
Prophet, <hi>Awake and ſing ye that dwell in the Dust; 
<note place="margin">Iſai. 26.19.</note> for thy dew is as the dew
of Herbs, and the Earth ſhall give up her Dead.</hi> 
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102410:9"/>As
the ſweet Dews or Showrs (as we commonly ſay) looſen many a Priſoner,
make Corn and Graſs to grow; ſo the Dew of heavenly Vertue and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
which flows from Chriſt, ſhall looſen many a Priſoner; raiſe our
Bodies, the Priſoners of Hope, from that dark Cell of the Grave, unto a
ſtate of Bleſſedneſs and Glory.</p>
            <p>And now ſince <hi>death is a ſleep,</hi> much may be learnt
hence for our Inſtruction and Comfort.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For Inſtruction, firſt, Unto a due and ſerious
preparation for it. We prepare our ſelves to ſleep, by ſetting aſide
all worldly Negotiations, giving to Body and Mind a Ceſſation from outward
Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: So ſhould we diſpoſe our ſelves to this laſt ſleep,
laying aſide all worldly Cares and Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. 
<note place="margin">2 Kings 20.1.</note> 
               <hi>Set thy Houſe in
order</hi> (ſaith the Prophet to <hi>Hezekiah</hi>) <hi>for thou muſt
dye.</hi> While the Houſe is out of order, the Mind is out of frame, and not
yet rightly compoſed to ſleep: Eſpecially the Soul it ſelf is to be
ſet in order, by ſerious Repentance, and unfeigned Reſolutions and
Endeavours of a new Life. It was <hi>Agurs</hi> Prayer, 
<note place="margin">Prov. 30.7.</note> 
               <hi>Two things have I
deſired of the Lord, before I dye.</hi> One is, <hi>Remove from me Vanity and
Lyes:</hi> Sin is often repreſented to us under the Notion of <hi>vanity and
lies</hi> (as in the ſourth <hi>Pſalm,</hi> and elſewhere) indeed a
<hi>lying vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> abuſing our Apprehenſions with the ſhadow and
appearance of a ſeeming good, but in the mean time betrays us to a real evil
of guilt and torment. This therefore ſhould be the chief care, aime and
endeavour of our whole Lives, not to <hi>dye in our ſins: But laying aſide
the ſin which beſets us about,</hi> as <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102410:10"/>Clothes do the
Body, 
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the
<hi>rotten raggs</hi> of the <hi>Old man,</hi> and ſo having made our peace
with God, we may be fit to lay down our heads in peace. Thus prepare thy ſelf
continually for this bleſſed Reſt, by renewing thy Repentance; fortifying
thy Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of better Obedience; confirming thy Intereſt in the Merits
and Mediation of Chriſt, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it ſhall pleaſe God to call
thee to Bed, thou may'ſt with a ſerene Conſcience, and a good
aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Hope, lay down thy dying head upon this Pillow, the free and
immerited Grace of God in Chriſt, and chearfully Commend thy Soul into his
hands, as into the hands of a faithful Creator and Redeemer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It teacheth Reſignation: When we ſleep we willingly
yield to Nature, without ſtrugling or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctation; ſo ſhould we unto the
God of Nature, when he calls us to this long ſleep; being not haled or drag'd
out of this Earthly Tabernacle, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly reſign it into the hands of
our great Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord. Our Death ſhould not be a violent Divulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but a
gentle Diſſolution. Mark St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, 
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.6. <hi>Nihil intereſt utrum abjures
depoſitum, aut doleas restitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I am now ready to be
offered;</hi> ready, as a <hi>Freewill Offering.</hi> God requires but what he
hath for a time lent us; and ſhall we be unwilling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore? We had as
good deny the Debt, as grieve to make Reſtitution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It teacheth hope of a Reſurrection. When men go to
ſleep, they put off their Clothes indeed, but expecting to put them on again
in the Morning; ſo we are to nouriſh in our ſelves this Faith, that
'though we uncloath our ſelves of this vile Body, <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102410:10"/>it is
not loſt, but put to the mending, to be changed in the faſhion, reſtored
to Immortality and Incorruptibility, <hi>and made like unto the glorious Body
of Chriſt.</hi> This for Inſtruction. Again, here is Matter of exceeding
Comfort,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, againſt the ſeeming horrour of the Grave:
That Death is but a ſleep, and differs only from it in this (which is its
advantage) ſoundneſs of Reſt, and perhaps length of Continuance. Fear not
then (O Chriſtian) the ſtink of Rottenneſs, horrour of Darkneſs,
gnawing of the Worms, &amp;c. theſe things ſhall not ſenſibly touch
thee. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of it rather as a Caſtle of Security, a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Reſt, a
Bed of Down, a Pillow of Eaſe, wherein thou ſhalt ſafely and ſweetly
reſt till the Morning of the Reſurrection. Truly therefore we may ſay, 
<note place="margin">Stultum eſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem horrere, &amp; ſomno
delectari.</note> It is a vain and fooliſh thing to delight to ſleep, yet
to be afraid to dye. Doſt thou go to Bed every Night, and art thou afraid to
go this once? Art thou not yet weary of hearing, ſeeing, doing, and
ſuffering ſo much evil? Art thou like a pettiſh Child, unwilling and
fearful to go to Bed? When therefore our time of ſleep approacheth, and that
we are called to reſt in our Fathers Boſom, let us be affected as good old
<hi>Hilarion; Go forth, 
<note place="margin">Egredere anima mea, egredere, quid times?</note>
O my Soul, go forth; What feareſt thou? My Body lye down and
ſleep.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This Comforts us againſt the Miſeries and Sufferings
of this preſent Life. Methinks when I look on Man, I ſee a deplorable
Creature, ſubject to innumerable Miſeries, hurried with Temptations,
diſtemper'd with Paſſions, 
<note place="margin">Job 7.2.</note> 
               <hi>as a Servant earneſtly
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring <pb n="16" facs="tcp:102410:11"/>the ſhadow, and as an hireling the reward of
his work.</hi> Chear up thy ſelf in this, that as the ſhadow of the Night
doth equally gratifie Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Servant, High and Low, Rich and Poor, with
the common benefit of Nature; ſo there is a time of ſleep and reſt
approaching, which will ſhut up our Miſeries with our Eyes, and end our
Labours with our Lives. Though here we have born the travail and heat of the
day, our Comfort is, we ſhall go to Bed at Night. It is recorded of
<hi>Babilas,</hi> that renowned Martyr, that when <hi>Decius</hi> the Emperour
commanded his Head to be chopt off; receiving that bloody Sentence with a
ſweet Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Serenity of Soul, he uſed only thoſe few words of
the <hi>Pſalmiſt, 
<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.7.</note> Return then unto thy
reſt, O my Soul.</hi> A bleſſed ſleep indeed; not as our Natural
ſleeps often are, troubled and ſhort; but reſtful without diſturbance;
bliſsful without pain and annoiance, and which ſhall not be ſtartled or
amazed with the voice of the <hi>Arch-Angel,</hi> and the <hi>Trump of
God:</hi> But both Body and Soul united, ſhall be put into poſſeſſion
of that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Eternal Reſt, which remains unto the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God.</p>
            <p>The third General part of the Text remains; which is the ſecond
Ground of Comfort, The hope of a bleſſed Reſurrection; implied in theſe
words; 
<q>Even as they that have no hope.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:102410:11"/>
            <p>The <hi>Hope</hi> here mentioned (as appears by the following
words) is of a <hi>bleſſed Reſurrection;</hi> and conſequently of
<hi>Eternal Glory:</hi> Where beſides a ſevere Reprehenſion of immoderate
Sorrow for the Dead, we have a ſolid ground of Comfort, both againſt the
Fear of Death, and Sorrow for deceaſed Chriſtians. And it is this; 
<q>That a Chriſtian is a Man of Hope.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Obſ. 3."/> It is not the will of God that we
ſhould preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter upon the Poſſeſſion of our Inheritance; but
that we ſhould be here in a ſtate of expectancy of that Bleſſing which
is depoſited, 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc ipſum quod ſumus Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni
ſpei res eſt.</hi> Pſal. 97.11.</note> laid up for us in Heaven: So that
a Chriſtian's Treaſure and Felicity conſiſts in Hope. <hi>Light is
ſowen for the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and Joy for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright in heart.</hi> But
ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and under the Clods here; the Harveſt is yet to come: <hi>It doth
not yet appear what we ſhall be;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Joh, 3.2.</note> our Happineſs here is in
Reverſion, not in preſent Poſſeſſion. And though God give us a
comfortable taſte of it, in the <hi>firſt fruits of the Spirit, Peace of
Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Joy in the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> the full fruition is
not till the Life to come.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> is firſt of
<hi>Inſtruction,</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. To inform us of the difference between the Children of
God and of this World; one is a man of hope, the other hopeleſs; one hath his
portion, and receiveth <hi>his good things</hi> here, the things of a better
Life he neither cares nor hopes for. For ſomething in preſent, though a
Poſſeſſion of Dirt, he is ready to forfeit all his great and glorious
hopes; with <hi>Eſau,</hi> preferring his <hi>pottage</hi> before his
<hi>birth-right.</hi> But the true Chriſtian is a man of hope, and hath
quitted the purſuit of things Temporal, for things Eternal. Therefore may
ſay to the Worldling, as our bleſſed <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102410:12"/>Saviour to his
Kinſmen in another caſe; <hi>your time is alway with you; but my time is
not yet come;</hi> much good may your Portion do you. I envy you not, I rather
pity you. I have other things to think of, of more worth and certainty: In the
mean time, my Soul ſhall reſt in hope.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To teach us to cheriſh this Hope by a godly and
Chriſtian Life. Hope and Holineſs, like <hi>Hyppocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> Twins, wax
and wain, riſe and fall, live and dye together. As we grow up in the true
fear of God, and conſcience of well-doing, we confirm our hope of eternal
Bleſſedneſs. 
<note place="margin">Acts 24.15.</note> 
                  <hi>We have hope toward
God</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that there ſhall be a Reſurrection
both of the juſt and unjuſt: And</hi> (for this hopes ſake) <hi>I
exerciſe my ſelf to have a Conſcience void of offence both toward God and
Man.</hi> Thus hope is nouriſht by the ſtudy of holineſs, as the light of
a Lamp is by the Oyl that feeds it: Therefore live well and hope well. 
<note place="margin">1 John 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>He that hath this hope
purifieth himſelf as God is pure.</hi> Again, here is matter of Comfort,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, Againſt the difficulties we meet with in the
courſe of Piety. There is naturally in us a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain tenderneſs ready to
ſink under Duty, unleſs born up and encourag'd with the hope of the
<hi>Prize ſet before us,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1.3.</note> St. <hi>Paul</hi>
ſpeaks of a <hi>work of Faith,</hi> and <hi>labour of Love;</hi> implying
ſome hard Enterpriſe. And what is the <hi>work of Faith?</hi> to march
conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt all Oppoſitions, to reſiſt Temptations, to
overcome the World, to endure hardſhip, <hi>as good Souldiers of Jeſus
Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>to perſevere</hi> in our holy purpoſes <hi>unto the
end.</hi> And what is the labour of Love? An unwearied induſtry and diligence
in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the good of others, with all good offices and fruits growing from
the root of Charity. Both theſe <pb n="19" facs="tcp:102410:12"/>are quickned by a hopeful
intuition of the Reward, which he calls in the next words, <hi>the patience of
hope.</hi> So having bleſſed God for the <hi>Colloſſians</hi> Faith and
Love, he points to that which ſupported both; 
<note place="margin">Col. 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>for the hopes ſake
which is laid up for us in Heaven.</hi> Without this hope, we ſhould deſire
and yet ſit ſtill; (like men languiſhing in ſtrength) purpoſe and be
weary of our own purpoſes; reſolve, and preſently loath our own
Reſolutions; but the patience of hope having an eye to the Crown, ſweetens
our Labours, perpetuates our Endeavours, and enables us with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible
Conſtancy to ſurmount all Difficulties, Thus hope by fortifying our
Reſolutions, and ſmoothing the roughneſs of the way, makes us to purſue
the good we aſpire to, with more heat and leſs pain. The Husbandman would
not ſo freely expoſe himſelf to toil and travail, wind and weather, but
for hopes ſake, which promiſeth him the Fruit of his Labour. The Souldier
would not caſt himſelf into ſo many horrid forms of dangers, ſcale
Walls, enter Breaches, thruſt himſelf into the fury of Combates, but for
hopes ſake of either Booty or Glory. The Merchant would not expoſe
himſelf to Waves and Storms, Rocks and Quick-ſands, but in hopes of a
golden Recompence: This will men do and ſuffer for (alas!) a poor ſhadow of
Wealth and Glory. Brethren, as a Chriſtians work is much more honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
ſo the reward ſet before us, to quicken faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vertue, is incomparably
more glorious. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let this hope in our boſomes encourage us, not only
patiently, but joyfully to tread upon all Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and conſidering the
joy that attends us in the end, to <hi>fix our eye, gird our loyns, gather up
our ſtrength, and run with patience the Race that is ſet before
us.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102410:13"/>
               <p n="2">2. Againſt the Sufferings and Afflictions of this
preſent Life: Let us not be diſmay'd with croſſes and loſſes of
whatſoever is deareſt to us, ſo long as the Treaſure of our Hope, our
Bank in Heaven is ſafe and untoucht. Hope is an excellent Receipt againſt
all Cardiack Paſſions; it hath a ſpecial virtue againſt fainting of the
heart, and therefore to be laid up in the boſom againſt all
diſtreſſes, eſpecially when the thing hoped for is ſo excellent.
<hi>Well yet</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth,
and that I ſhall one day ſee him;</hi> when his <hi>reins</hi> were
<hi>conſumed within him.</hi> And this wrought in him a patient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
of betters things; <hi>All the days of my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time will I wait till my
change come;</hi> a change from ſin and miſery, to happineſs and glory.
We ſee by experience, that even natural hope ſolaceth the Soul in all
Afflictions; it tells us there is no impoſſibility of Emergency, and
riſing out of the deepeſt Miſeries; that Humane Calamities have their
bounds, and will not always tyre themſelves about one Man; that there is
ſucceſſion of Storms and Calms in the courſe of Mans life, that
unexpected ways of relief may happen: Such is the Viciſſitude of Earthly
things. If there be the leaſt chink or cranny to let in any Beam of Comfort,
<hi>Hope</hi> will not lightly fail. <hi>Natural Hope</hi> therefore is an
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Anchor in the Troubleſom Sea of this World. But (alas) oft-times
the Cable breaks, our Hope ſpends it ſelf in Vain Imaginations, and in the
end makes us aſhamed. 
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Heb. 6.11.</note> But
this <hi>Hope;</hi> as the end is more certain, ſo the Aſſurance more
full. A full Aſſurance of Hope, and ſo of far greater virtue to ſupport
the Soul. It hath made the glorious <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> to ſuffer the loſs of
all things, of Life it ſelf; <pb n="21" facs="tcp:102410:13"/>not accepting deliverance
(that is, upon baſe terms, and with loſs and prejudice of their Faith) that
they might obtain a better Reſurrection. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Hope carries us but to
our Lives end; that's the utmoſt Verge of it: <hi>While I live, I hope to
live.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dum ſpiro ſpero, cnm expiro
ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro.</note> But the Grace of <hi>Hope</hi> carries us further: <hi>When
dead, I hope to live;</hi> and therefore let Health, 
<note place="margin">The Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hath hope in his death.
<hi>Prov.</hi> 14.32.</note> Wealth, Liberty, Friends, yea Life and Breath, and
all go; yet I will hold faſt the hope of <hi>Joy</hi> that is ſet before
me. Though therefore we dwell here as <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom;</hi> our Souls
vexed, tortured with the ſinful Vanities of Men, there is hope of a Day when
every thing that offends ſhall be caſt out. Though our ſincere endeavours
to pleaſe God be derided by the Profane World; there is hope of a Time
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when our <hi>Judgment ſhall break forth as the light, and our
Righteouſneſs as the Noon day;</hi> when we ſhall have <hi>Beauty</hi>
for our <hi>Aſhes,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> for our <hi>Shame.</hi> Do we
groan under the burthen of Sin, the rebellion of <hi>Nature</hi> againſt
<hi>Grace,</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh</hi> againſt the <hi>Spirit?</hi> there is
hope of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of <hi>Weakneſs</hi> for <hi>Power, Imperfection</hi>
for <hi>Perfection, Neceſſity of ſinning</hi> for a <hi>Confirmed ſtate
of obeying.</hi> Thus Hope ſupports the Spirits, and keeps us from Sowning.
It ſeems, St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſometime a little diſpirited and out of
heart; but revives preſently: and what was his Cordial? Hope of the
<hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and the conſequent <hi>Glory; That this light
affliction, which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, worketh to us a far more exceeding and
eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal weight of glory.</hi> If our Hopes were termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated within the narrow
bounds of this Life, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity were at a poor ſtay, and Chriſtians of
all Men moſt miſerable; (ſo cold entertainment doth <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102410:14"/>it find in the World) but being Anchored <hi>within the Vail,</hi> we
are of all Men moſt happy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To Conclude, as I began; This ſhould mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate our
Sorrow for them that are Dead in the Lord; That they breathed out their Souls
in hope; that their <hi>fleſh rests in hope,</hi> and their Bodies in Graves
are but Priſoners of Hope; and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union with us in a glorious and
Triumphant Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, 
<note place="margin">In quo non poteſt ſubeſſe
fulſum.</note> is the matter alſo of our Hope. And though a Fiducial and
Infallible aſſurance of anothers final Happineſs (while they are yet in
the ſtate of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers) none can have, without ſpecial Revelation. ('Tis
well if we can attain this Aſſurance to our ſelves, with all diligence
and much difficulty, by many degrees <hi>working out our ſalvation with fear
and trembling;</hi>) yet for them that have <hi>fought a good fight,</hi> and
<hi>finiſhed their courſe</hi> in the true Faith and fear of God; well may
we have an erected <hi>Hope</hi> of a glorious and eternal Aſſociation, and
that <hi>together with them we ſhall for ever be with the Lord; 
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 7.</note>
wherefore comfort one another with theſe words.</hi> Indeed, a ſolid ground
of Chriſtian Conſolation in this ſhort Temporal privation of our
deareſt Friends, and ſuch as the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who were <hi>without
Chriſt,</hi> the ground of Hope; without the Church, the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of Hope;
without the Covenant of Grace, the Reaſon of our Hope, could not afford.
Thoſe Cordials that are fetch'd out of Natures Boxes; That <hi>Death</hi> is
the common end of All; 
<note place="margin">Mors exitus communis, ea lege
naſcimus.</note> that it is the Law and Condition of our Birth, are but cold
Comforts, in compariſon of that which Chriſtian Hope holds forth unto us:
<hi>And therefore, Bleſſed be God and the Father of our Lord Jeſus
Chriſt, who hath begotten us again unto a lively hope, by the 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102410:14"/>Reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead; to an
inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance immortal, incorruptible, undefiled, that fadeth not away,
reſerved for us in Heaven.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p>And now my Diſcourſe, like a Circle, is return'd to the
Point where I began, <hi>viz.</hi> This truly Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, Noble, Courteous,
Dearly beloved Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. A great Treaſury, though exhauſted; a ſhining
Light, quenched; a burning glorious Lamp, extinguiſhed, a ſweet, delicious,
comly, fragrant Flower, cropt and fading; a bright Star of a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed
magnitude, removed from our Horizon, and well may Darkneſs cover this
Hemiſphere. Here I could willingly ſit down a while in ſilence, and only
by the language of our Tears, ſpeak our ſenſe of this heavy Loſs; but
(as I have new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Diſcours'd) all Paſſions, eſpecially that of
<hi>Grief,</hi> need rather a Bridle than a Spur. Let therefore the Thoughts of
his Superlative Merits, while living, and the Inexpreſſible Glories he is
now in poſſeſſion of, bring down the Sluce a while, and dam up the
ſtreaming Fountain of our <hi>Tears</hi> and <hi>Sorrow,</hi> whilſt, to
his moſt deſervedly Worth and Memory, and our abundant Delight and Comfort,
we pay that Tribute of <hi>Praiſe</hi> that is due to Gods Servants and
Children; advancing thereby his Glory, and adding Spurs to the Pious Endeavours
of thoſe who Survive. And that I may the more both ſuitably and
ſuccinctly delineate thoſe Graces, which though they are gone with him, for
his Comfort, yet ſtay behind him, for his Honour and our Imitation.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:102410:15"/>
               <p>Be pleaſed to veiw him in the Method of theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
Particulars:</p>
               <p>Firſt, In his <hi>Birth;</hi> There we may ſee great
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies deſcended to him by his Progenitors. To be born of a good
Family, and to be well Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is a Mercy not to be neglected; <hi>Nec
imbellem progenerant aquilae columbam,</hi> ſaith <hi>Horace.</hi> You have
read of Mr. <hi>Philpots</hi> zealous Martyrdom; 
<note place="margin">V. 2. Examin. of Mr. <hi>Philpot. Acts</hi>
and <hi>Mon.</hi> Vol. 3. Dr. <hi>Wilk.</hi> H. gl.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Knights
Son, told his Perſecutors, <hi>He was a Gentleman.</hi> Anabaptiſtical
parity, and Levelling de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, are ever to be abhord, and look'd upon as the
ready way to Rapine, Confuſion, and Violence. To be born of Noble Parents,
from a Family that is not ſtain'd nor ſullied with the foul ſpots of
<hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> and <hi>Rebellion;</hi> nor tainted with the Seeds of
<hi>Error, Schiſm,</hi> and <hi>Diviſion;</hi> nor baſely dirted with the
black filth of <hi>Debauchery, Atheiſm, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs,</hi> and
<hi>Irreligion;</hi> (all which is eminently true without Flattery, in this
Gentlemans <hi>Eſcutche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) queſtionleſs, is one of Gods choice
Bleſſings: And to a Mind inclining to Vertue, it availeth much to be born
well; <hi>Eſt aliquid clarus magnorum ſplendor avorum</hi>— The
glorious Deſerts of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Parents, is no ſmall Patrimony
—<hi>ſed vix ea noſtra a voco</hi>—</p>
               <p>Secondly, Therefore conſider him in his own
<hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> And in that, firſt his Outward, and then ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his
Inward Ornaments, Grace, and Perfections. His <hi>Body</hi> of exact ſymmetry
and proportion, where we might behold a great ſhare of Comlineſs and
Beauty, which God our Creator (the Fountain of all <hi>Beauty</hi>) had
imparted to this lovely Creature; and in ſuch a meaſure, as if
<hi>Mother-Nature</hi> had called a Councel, and took a more than ordinary care
and <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102410:15"/>coſt in its firſt draught and lineaments: But when
it became poliſh'd, by an ingenious and liberal Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; every ſtep and
motion in his Deportment, was a prevailing Argument to beget both Love and
Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, And all this is as far Inferior to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
Perfections, as the ſhining of the Gold-Ring, in compariſon of that
luſtre and ſplendid Excellency, which the Artificially Cut and well-ſet
<hi>Diamond</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords the Spectator. When firſt Judgment and the uſe of
Reaſon began to open and perform its Acts, how induſtrious was he to
impreſs good Habits! That that Seaſon might be improved to Vertue, which in
many Children is too prone to Liberty; accuſtoming himſelf to good Manners,
before he was fully comprehenſive of a greater Knowledge and Underſtanding.
And when at any time (whilſt under my Tuition) any thing ſeem'd difficult
to his obtaining; in that very particular, the goodneſs of a ſweet
Diſpoſition ſo eminently appeared, That did not Court and Complement an
Indulgence from me, but ſubdue by Conqueſt. And ever as His days and years
increaſed, ſo did alſo a moſt Accompliſh'd model of his Duty toward
God and Man. How of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten have I (when expecting to have interrupted his Innocent
Divertiſements by a ſudden ſurpriſal) found, to my great Comfort, this
hopeful and pious Bloſſom in a Saint-like poſture on his knees to God,
with two or three gathered together, tendring his Morning Sacrifice? Nor was it
done by fits, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted by Fear, or a ſevere Diſcipline; but a
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and Free-will Offering. Had you ſeen that pithy and ſuitable
Form of Prayer annexed in his firſt Grammar, ſlubber'd and defac'd by his
tender <pb n="26" facs="tcp:102410:16"/>hands, with his daily peruſal; it would be no
great wonder, that God ſhould ſo ſoon remove him to ſing
<hi>Allelujahs</hi> in the <hi>Choire</hi> of Heaven, that had ſo early and
ſo well perform'd it on Earth. He that had ſo ſoon vers'd himſelf in
the Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, contain'd in the <hi>Church-Catechiſm,</hi> to
the delight of his Earthly Parents, could not long be detain'd from being made
perfect with Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to the glory and honour of his Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
He, in whom there was ſuch a fruitful Spring of all imaginable good hopes of
doing good in his Generation among Men, is now glorifying God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
Angels; as the one, in deep Sighs and ſad Accents of Lamentations bewails our
great loſs; ſo the other, as a moſt ſtrong Cordial ſhould revive our
drooping Souls. Many excellent things might be communicated unto you, not only
for Imitation, but Admiration. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. tells
us, <hi>In a great houſe there are veſſels of Gold, ſome to honour,
ſome to diſhonour.</hi> Give me leave to borrow his Metaphor; <hi>In this
Noble houſe, this great Family, He was a choice Veſſel.</hi> What
<hi>Euſebius</hi> calls his Beloved Friend, I may well apply unto him; he was
<hi>Vas Virtutum admirabile,</hi> A Veſſel adorn'd with an admirable
variety of Natural Abilities, Moral Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and Spiritual Graces, every way
ſuitable to his Birth, Quality, and Education. O that all the Sons of Honour
of this Kingdom, and Off-ſpring of good Blood, had the like Pious and early
Inclinations to good Literature and Education! Such Ambitious Thoughts, to be
eminent in Knowledge and Piety! Such Sentiments of the
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities!</hi> Such Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere to the Members thereof! Such value and
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem to their Parts and Merits! Then I ſhould be <pb n="27" facs="tcp:102410:16"/>in
greater Hopes of ſeeing a flouriſhing State and Kingdom: Then would there
be more Amicable Overtures between the Church and State. I dare be bold to
ſay it, That there is nothing ſooner likely to weaken and prevent, if not
expoſe and ruine the flouriſhing State of this or any Kingdom, than the
want of ſound Learning and Exemplary Lives in the Nobility and Gentry
thereof. I cannot omit the imparting one thing obſervable in this young Hero,
at his firſt entrance to make his own Conceptions into <hi>Latin;</hi> in
order thereunto I gave him this Subject, <hi>Ignorantia est ſola inimica
Doctrinae,</hi> i.e. <hi>Ignorance is the alone Enemy to Learning;</hi> which
made ſuch impreſſions upon his tender Thoughts, that (in his moſt free
Converſation with thoſe, that the Hoſpitable Houſe-keeping of his
Honourable Parents, gave many and frequent Opportunities for) He daily
obſerved thoſe Perſons, to have the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Thoughts, not only of
Clergy-men, but of all others whatſoever under any Coat or Garb, if Learned,
whoſe Education and Scholarſhip could carry them very little further than
to Write and Read. I have a large field to turn me in, where I might expatiate
in his juſt and due Character, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone out like a <hi>Taper,</hi> that
hath left a ſweet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour behind him in the Noſtrils of all that knew him:
But I am willing to contract my ſelf, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I am contain'd in the
preſcrib'd limits of ſuch Time as may be moſt ſuitable to the Offices
of this Nature. And what ſhould I ſay more? for the Time would fail me to
tell of his <hi>Humility, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Modeſty, Courteſie, Condeſcending
to thoſe of low Eſtate;</hi> the great Aims and Ambition to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<hi>Duty to his Parents, Love to his Friends, <pb n="28" facs="tcp:102410:17"/>Familiarity
with his Neighbour, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmoveable affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to his Servants, Lowlineſs to his
Inferiours, Reſpect to his Superiours, Kindneſs to his Equals,</hi> and
<hi>Inſuperable Goodneſs to his dearest and neareſt Relatives.</hi> Thus
he left the World, <hi>having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd a good report through Faith,</hi> Heb.
11.39. in the flower and firſt budding of his days, upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines and
borders of the 16th year of his Age, at the Feet of <hi>Gamallel,</hi> newly
placed in a ſtation of good Literature, in a Conſtellation of Arts and
Sciences, in that Ancient Foundation of <hi>Exeter-Colledge,</hi> long ſince
Laid by the Learned and Charitable <hi>Walter Stapleton,</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Exeter,</hi> amongſt the young Glories of our preſent ſtate,
univerſally Lamented, univerſally Beloved, in his <hi>Virgin-purity</hi>
unſtain'd and unſpotted; nowly Eſpouſed (with the joyful Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation
of Parents on both ſides) to a Lady whoſe promiſing Excellencies, not
only of a conſiderable Fortune, but of <hi>Vertue, Youth, Beauty, good
Nature, good Parentage,</hi> and all ſuch commendable Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as
might have in all appearing probabilities, rendred them both as happy as our
Deſires and Wiſhes could have expected, and their Worths me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited and
deſerved. O! But that God, that rules and governs all things by his Wiſdom
and Providence, the reaſons and cauſes of the various effects whereof, are
Subjects to employ the eyes of our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> but not to
be diſcover'd in Proſpectives of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Reaſon) ſent an Hoſt of
Heavenly Spirits, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and recal that Spirit (he himſelf firſt
breathed) to the celebration of Nuptials of an higher Nature, with <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt</hi> the great Bridegroom of departed Saints, in the Beatifical
Viſion of the all glorious Trinity, <hi>the Father of an Infinite Majeſty,
the true <pb n="29" facs="tcp:102410:17"/>and only Son, the Holy Ghoſt the Comforting and
San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſhall we now either irrationally complain? or
religiouſly murmure and repine at? or uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly envy at his glorious
Tranſlation? He is inlarg'd from the Priſon of this Life, and ſhall we
bemoan his Liberty? He has quickly weathered through the diſturb'd Waves in
the unquiet Sea of this World; and ſhall we in a miſtaken Zeal debar him
the quiet Haven? Unwiſe Mortals that we are! Is there any Earthly
Inheritances, Crowns, or Dignities, that could court him into a Return, or an
Exchange, for thoſe Manſions of Eternal Glory, he is in poſſeſſion
of? No, no; his Gains in his removal, are of ſuch a Nature, both for Body,
Soul, Eſtate, Place, and Company, as can neither be ſufficiently
expreſſed, or conceived, by Human Wit and Invention: For his Body, that is
ſtript of all ſinful and natural De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, the Abortions of Sin, and fill'd
with all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Contemplations at its reunion with the Soul; of Mortal, it
becomes Immortal; of Corruptible, Incorruptible; of Natural, Spiritual, <hi>i.
e.</hi> not need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing natural helps: There is no uſe of Meats, Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel,
Phyſick, Sleep, Beds; of weak and infirm, glorious: And for his Soul, that is
firſt eas'd of all the Rags and Reliques of Sin; delivered of Igno rance and
Self-love; delivered of all the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Sin, Griefs, Fears, Guilts,
Accuſations: And then it is filled with the Image of Jeſus; then all the
Powers and Faculties are advanced above the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſtrain of Nature; and
his Soul furniſhed with all the Attendances of Chriſt's Image,
everlaſting Joy, perpetual Peace, a conſtant Correſpondence and Communion
with God and his Holy Angels.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:102410:18"/>
               <p>And here we leave him; But it is but for a ſhort time; the
Diviſion betwixt him and us is of a ſmall continuance; we muſt ſuddenly
cut over the ſame Ferry, and meet him on the other ſide of the Shore;
Death's Boat was not appointed to carry all at once; the Ferry not made to land
all at one Tide; ſtay the return of Water for our turn: <hi>In the mean time
praying for a proſperous Gail, and giving God thanks for all his Servants
departed this Life in his Faith and Fear, beſeeching him to give us Grace to
follow their good Example, that with them we may be partakers of his heavenly
Kingdom, through Jeſus Chriſt our Mediatour and Advocate, To whom, with the
Father and the Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, and one God, be aſcrib'd all
Honour, Adoration, and Thankſgiving now, and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102410:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
